I was watching a YouTube video before
you came in and um I think that was on
what I have two key lights I have a big
Elgato key light here and a little key
light over here and they're both
supposed to connect to Wi-Fi so that I
can control the temperature and the
intensity of the light with one app and
the big light the big light is connected
the little light is not I can't get the
little Wi-Fi like indicator like to come
on so I was watching a video on how to
set it up and uh I haven't figured it
out yet but okay well your lighting
looks fine it's like a warm light I know
I was trying to lighten it because you
should have seen it before I looked like
I had I was gonna be like hey we're
coming back off of three weeks of not
recording and I got a
tan yeah bet yeah that would be that
would be great my ta my tax SE in tan
yeah no that doesn't happen that doesn't
happen dreams you just starting them way
ahead at the end scenes started reading
and dodging all of the quick schemes
money like your Spotify boy
[Music]
gots I am Daniel I'm Sarah and this is
inquisitive episode
11 coming back after a few weeks of not
recording but we are still talking about
deals that fail to close because we
aren't here to sell you the fake dream
of running a business Halfway Around The
World from your sailboat in the
Mediterranean because that most of the
time doesn't happen in fact most deals
don't close so we're breaking down why
deals don't close and why they struggle
to close and helping you learn from
others mistakes timeline just the the
order of
operations in events and it sounds like
um Daniel you did not spend tax season
on the
beach you were busy yes I I do still own
uh so I talk a lot about business
brokering and Acquisitions but I do
still own an online account firm called
profit and grow and uh we do taxes for
our clients and yes I was uh very very
busy it more busy this year than I've
been in a while actually like I um I try
to get it done so much sooner but I I
really wanted to avoid a heavy extension
season so I got the vast majority of our
work done before the initial deadline
which is great because now I can focus
on year-end planning for my clients
rather than taxes in you know October
that is nice
I wasn't super pleased with my situation
because I had to follow up three times
and be like hey are are we going to file
an extension or what's the plan and then
finally got an estimated payment which
was six figures and and they were like
so we can just draft that out of your
checkin account any second now just let
us know and I was like um who do you
think I am you know I'm going to have to
move some money around obviously and it
required additional days so I was at the
farm where we were throwing our party
like trying to connect to an old printer
that was you know in the back of a like
covered in straw
dust getting something printed so I can
authorize a being pulled from a money
market or whatever I mean there's
probably accountants out there that are
just Psychopaths but I have to tell you
like in my experience we are sweating
bullets when we are reaching out to tell
like we do it with confidence and we're
like you got to pay $100,000 in taxes
and we just like but it's like pulling a
Band-Aid it's like just say it like
$100,000 in taxes hope hope you got that
thanks uh Hey here here's the link yeah
in their defense I was traveling and
they emailed like hey we just need to
get on a like a just a quick call and
explain some stuff to you so you know
what's going on and you could just like
read the stress but like I can do math
it's not I know I'm going to pay a lot
in taxes so it's anticipa
and I have money put away for that
purpose that's been in a money market um
So I responded that email I was like I
don't think we need a call what's the
number so yeah they're just freaking out
but but the money market thing it's
something that's so interesting because
um you know I don't know I try to be
like a non-traditional tax professional
yeah and I have I I worked with some
wealth managers that really turned me
onto this idea that I mean I have to
tell people to make estimated payments
right but the way the penalty calculates
out doesn't typically I mean it's it's
pretty far off of what you can get on an
average return from the market yeah so
like a high yield savings account or
money market account like often makes
more sense yeah um and it's tough like I
don't know I I have a client and he
watches these so he's gonna see this um
but he wanted me to you know wants me to
calculate it and I I do I'm going to do
it this is my first year I'm actually
going to calculate the benefit to not
paying estimated taxes um he watches
this the IRS does not so I'm going to
make him happy and if the IRS starts
watching these and they are not happy
well call me you have my
number yeah please slide into our DM's
IRS we look forward to you um and also
get back to work you've got you've got a
lot to do um no that's a I did kind of
under that assumption because I did
um cost segregation study um short-term
rental loophole thing um which meant my
estimated payments for last year were
like nothing because I they based on
your tax liability for the year prior so
I knew I was not chipping away at any
tax liability this whole time so the
whole time I was putting money into this
money market and I ound up making like
$2,500 in interest which wasn't that
much on you know 100K um so I was like
was this more trouble than it was worth
if it had delayed if I had had some
penalty from like the delay of getting
the money to pay the um IRS and I would
have probably wiped that out pretty
quick so well you should hit the safe
har yeah you should hit the Safe Harbor
numbers and even if you didn't it would
be like a relatively nominal failure to
prepaid penalty so it's like yeah now
next this year you know you should yeah
game on game on you know yeah pay yeah
pay something yeah yeah um or or make a
whole lot of money with your Investments
so that it's worth the failure to prepay
penalty that's why I have everything in
crypto
no I was joking about getting call from
the IRS
um all right for the record I am not
Sarah Sharp's tax
professional yeah I do not yeah but he
does advise his clients to put
everything in
crypto so but it's a yeah you you do
recommend that Russian based crypto no
I'm just
kidding stressing me out yeah you're
getting so
nervous don't worry none of that real I
don't even know if that's a thing um it
just sounds like it might be however I
did have like $10,000 invested in crypto
and it's doing great nice yeah
everything is uh everything is seems
like up right now in crypto I stay away
from crypto crypto is not my game yeah I
just wanted to understand it so
sometimes you need a dog in the fight um
to stay engaged it makes the news more
interesting if you've
got it's also why I don't actually look
at the weather forecast because I really
enjoy the um authenticity it gives to my
casual conversations with people when
they're like see it's going to rain
tomorrow and I'm like really what it's
so pretty today yeah like a lot or a
little do you know
so um I enjoy
getting those updates from just passers
by um but we did so you were doing tax
season and I was um at our family farm
throwing a several hundred person
Eclipse party for the total solar
eclipse where the weather was perfect I
saw the pictures it looked beautiful
looked like a great time way more people
than I anticipated like when you said
you were having an eclipse party I was
like okay never heard of that but um and
we don't have a ton of them so I
guess but that was like that was a lot
of people is that all F family friends
and family is a small town um we had the
picture I sent you was a fraction we had
uh 250 name tags we ran out of name tags
um and I think Scott my father-in-law um
smokes uh hams and um he said well I I
Googled how many hams you need to feed
this many people that said 8 to 10 so I
did
14 we ran out of it so it was um it was
Rowdy we had about maybe 50 people drive
from Denver which it's like somewhere
between 15 and 20 hour drive is
ridiculous um and my friends from high
school drove up from lots of people from
Atlanta the Carolinas like not short
drives anywhere it's not proximal to
anything um but full totality so
it was very fun so and then the next
weekend we went down to Atlanta for a
wedding and I have our friend who is
originally from Nigeria so it was like a
big Rowdy Nigerian wedding which was
lots of fun so that's how I spent my
last bit of tax season which my life
focusing on accounting practice buyouts
is somewhat contrast cyclical so my tax
season is like a delight and very you
know chill and then it starts really
buckling down now right after tax season
when people realize they want to sell
their practices so I was thinking about
this uh during the so I was looking into
stuff about the eclipse and I did find
out so um as an introvert you probably
know that I don't like to throw parties
and I need plenty plenty of time to plan
so I was thinking that the next eclipse
actually crosses right over where I live
in Florida so I wanted to invite you to
my Eclipse party oh no I'm already
otherwise occupied
I know it's in
2045 because as totality is odd it also
is full totality in our mountain house
so you were invited to our cabin as well
deal deal forget yeah yeah I mean you'll
be at like the tree line 11,300 feet
altitude so
closer oxygen like can I we have an
oxygen
tank really
I was joking I live at sea
level so your your whole head will
explode
if like a chip bag um you might want to
take you know stop in Denver for a
couple days to acclimate um but yeah so
then anyways the point of all of that is
re relative to
timeline and um that was kind of what we
were talking about because we're both
dealing with different uh client issues
where um and I had one of these calls
yesterday where somebody said yeah I
think I need to buy this business now
like what what happens is there an Loi
and then I think from talking the
question that they were asking me she
seemed to think that um maybe that was
the whole thing like the letter of
intent was all of the legal work part of
things and she had plans to get a bank
loan but um she said yeah I told my
banker but I'm not sure what kind of
loan uh you know the banker is going to
give me and you're like I don't you know
just the way she was phrasing it gave me
pause that maybe she really like hadn't
oriented herself in you the spectrum of
just the different steps along the way
and kind of how
um specifically she needed to Champion
the um the banking process and you can't
you really shouldn't go to just you know
the bank you have your like your auto
loan with and get an SBA loan that's not
your best bet usually you kind of need
to shop this loan and it's not
necessarily like a mortgage where you
can just rely on your real estate broker
to you know do all of it for you you've
kind of got to lead that process um so I
connected her with um some banks and I
feel like bank I feel like Bankers have
a nasty habit of thinking that they're
the only Bank in the world yeah so so
they're like oh yeah we can't like that
can't be done it's like H you can't it
can be done like I I had a commercial
lender try to do that so it's like
a okay I'm be more careful about how I
talk about this um a commercial lender
the bank does do SBA but they are not a
preferred lender um they do asset backed
loans like the SBA is just like not
their thing and um yeah they they looked
at a deal and they were like yeah this
can't be financed this is not this
doesn't qualify and um the buyer thought
that meant this doesn't qualify by SBA
standards but in reality it's just
because they were looking at it through
the lens of an asset back loan rather
than a cash flow back loan and it's a
beautiful deal for a cash flow lender
yes so yeah I know it's a that's a major
component that people don't realize they
think like oh just go to the bank where
I have a relationship but they don't
they just don't know they don't and and
why would you right like we just live in
this world all day long every day but
before this I didn't know that either
and um so saying there's two you know
with the loan thing people come to me
and um they're on one end of the
spectrum sometimes they're like this
person who said you know I talked to my
banker and you know she you know the
banker said it can't be done or that
there's some kind of loan for it and
you're like oh no you need to really get
on get moving because this is clearly it
was like a $2 million um practice
acquisition should um like add on to an
existing practice so you're not going to
get like a helck probably that's GNA be
big enough that you can finance that
whole thing you're really looking at an
SBA 7A loan and that's a big process so
you got to get the ball rolling or they
come in and they're like I've talked to
13 lenders and I have term sheets at six
Banks and you're
like okay you need to narrow it down a
little because if you keep moving it
Forward at all of these different banks
you're never going to get all the way
through so it's time like there is no
perfect deal whatever small couple
thousand dollar fee difference you're
going to ultimately sus out is going to
be wiped away if you delay your um your
deal because you're still shopping with
banks and you haven't moved it Forward
aggressively so right so I mean yeah
we've we've talked to some great experts
about why deals fail in due diligence
why deals fail at the closing table but
I think like real istically most deals
don't make it to closing but the vast
majority of those that fail to close
also fail before due diligence like they
they almost like fail to start right
like so you um you know you you're
searching you find one you talk to the
seller you sign the NDA and and then
what like yeah you know then you kind of
fall off and then and then somebody else
swoops in they they put in their Loi or
they put in a purchase agreement like
they get aggressive about it and then
you just get passed up or you know you
think you made all this progress this
actually happened to me like true story
um I went through a month and a half of
negotiating the LOI all the way up to
like starting the bank process and then
like needing to do the the yeah like and
and it's because my Loi took so long so
like order of operations wise it you
know probably like made sense but in
reality like that stretches that deal
out so so far so going back would you
you would go and run those um two
uh paths in tandem so you'll be moving
it forward with the bank at the same
time that you were moving forward the
LOI or would you some some options are
people doing an ioi which is just like
an indication of interest if the bank
really needs one to get started and
that's just like purchase price and two
signatures basically so then you can get
them moving so I'm doing a version of an
ioi on everything and this is like
something that's I know I know some like
uh some more experienced Brokers are
like it's not step you don't need to
take but I like it and I do it for a
specific reason so the way I get an ioi
is I ask an interested buyer to send me
an email just send me an email that
expressing your interest in this tell me
a range of what you think is a normal
price for this like you don't have to
give me something specific just give me
arrange so we know we're in the ballpark
and give me a bio like tell me a little
bit about you so that I can present you
to the seller so that you know you're
you have an NDA I'm going to give you
the Sim give me this letter of interest
this indication of interest in the form
of an email I will present you to them
and then we move to the interview
between the two of you and then you
draft that that Loi and um or well we'll
get to those there's a Nuance there but
um I think what I would have done is I
would have probably pushed back on
negotiating the LOI so much and I would
have been like hey no this is the bones
of the deal like this is what we're
rolling with let me get into due
diligence and let me get the loan
process started and then we can
renegotiate when we get to the purchase
agreement like we don't need to have
agle the LOI so long interesting that's
the opposite of the advice I give people
but well I'm not going to okay so let's
talk about so your advice so your advice
is to to haggle out the LOI and to get
closer to final terms yeah if you um if
you're gonna and and
perhaps positing it worked the way it
was intended for you because the goal is
that you haven't paid a dumb lawyer like
me thousands of dollars to bury all
those terms you're going to disagree
about and to 30 pages of contracts you
can just keep figuring out whether or
not you're G to agree on them or not um
and then ultimately you don't agree you
don't agree and you haven't wasted a
bunch of money on lawyers um or somewhat
worse is by the time you know it's a
letter of intent pretty short and it
just it's like here's the deal terms the
purchase agreement is longer and it's
embedded in a lot more legal e um so
sometimes people get to the purchase
agreement and they lose sight of the
terms that they don't actually agree on
and then they just sign the document
never actually having a meeting of the
minds and that's um an outcome that some
lawyers almost misw want because they I
think they they think aha it'll be a
gotcha but I think those are people
who've never run a business and been in
the situation like so what if you have a
gacha on the other party and you're
sitting across from them and you're
trying they don't want to do something
that you want to do you then have to
show them they signs that they would do
it and it's just like a really
unpleasant T like you're going to force
them you're threatening to sue them to
do the thing like you and then you're
counting on them for transition so you
have to the buyer then has to work with
that person for you know three six 12
months yeah that's not a good situation
to be in to have a gacha and be able to
you know basically Force someone to do
what you want when they don't want to um
it's much better to have that
conversation at the LOI stage in my view
and actually develop a meeting of the
minds before you and then you sail
through the purchase agreement process
which can um that process when you draft
a purchase agreement you um so the way
it goes is II you know indication of
interest if if you're asked for one an
NDA happen and then an Loi is negotiated
you start your bank loan process with
your Loi if you're the buyer um the
diligence process is undergoing and um
you have those terms from the LOI they
might get modified in the diligence
process um I keep a transaction
checklist that's essentially like a
Google sheet so it's like Loi terms and
then each term has a column for how it's
renegotiated through the diligence
process if it is and then when you get
to the purchase agreement you put all of
that into the transaction documents you
the buyer initiates the transaction
documents sends them to the seller the
seller's attorney reviews makes red
lines changes or just accepts them
sometimes which is Eerie and then you
send them to the bank to approve the
bank might make redlines and changes
that then you have to send to the seller
and get everybody on board but once it's
signed you're good um that process that
I just described with the buyer seller
and the purchase agreement uh is the
most tiring for people because you're
sitting on these calls with lawyers and
you're looking at 30 page agreements
where they're like very boringly
explaining to you indemnification and
you know equivocating like it's a
business judgment call I say as somebody
decides whether they want to have a
liability cap of a million dollars or
whatever it's a very it's like pulling
teeth to go through that process so
anything you can do in the LOI phase
where you still fresh and have energy to
make that phase go faster and be less
painful I think is worth doing yeah that
absolutely makes sense so I think we
kind of went to the middle of the onion
so let's I I'd love to get your thoughts
on something because I I kind I think I
know how you're going to feel about this
but so I'm dealing I have a deal right
now and I'm the broker on this deal and
um small business it's a million dollar
it'll be a subm million dollar deal and
it's a basic business not a ton of due
diligence to do and uh buyers trying to
figure out next steps you know we're
kind of at that stage where you know
there's it's not really moving we're not
really moving forward and it doesn't
like maybe doesn't make much sense to
stop at the LOI phase if we could put
together a draft of a purchase agreement
that includes a clause for due diligence
or a Time period for due diligence and
you there there will be a transaction
lawyer that's going to help with the
closing but it neither s side's going to
it doesn't look like either side's going
to lawyer up on actually going through
and negotiations and prep preparation of
the document so um as a lawyer I'm going
ask you this like kind of CounterPoint
um is there a small enough deal where
you don't do an Loi where you actually
do just go to the purchase agreement you
do a templated purchase agreement
provided by a broker or you know some
third party resource and you have that
set up with contingencies I get the
appeal of that for sure especially from
your perspective because you're like
everyone's generally on the same page
it's a good fit there's no lawyers in
the room like let's just move this
forward um I have seen a ton of the uh
broker proferred uh purchase agreement
templates a lot of times my clients will
say oh they already gave us a template
to use and you know I I know that it'll
cost more money for me to revise their
template than it will be for me to just
use my documents that are good and
vetted um and the ultimate um work
product will be better if we start from
scratch so I just tank those um but I
didn't used to I used to like try to
work with them because you know Brokers
have seen so many deals um and they're
not good usually like they're they um
they typically have have things in them
that are worse than having no contract
um so you know ideally you have a
contract a written contract between you
and another party um I would rather you
have no written contract and just a
verbal agreement then have a contract
that everyone signed that has a whole
bunch of harmful stuff in it which is
usually what it has um and at bare
minimum they always have a bunch of
weird indemnifications related to the
broker um so it's it's usually like a
third just protective stuff that
protects the broker and then nothing
that actually identifies the terms
nobody reads it it doesn't actually
reflect the deal on the table at all it
becomes really it gets out of hand so I
know it gets uncomfortable I know so
many Brokers are in the position where
um nobody has a lawyer and they're kind
of
playing attorney in the middle um and it
can be uh uncomfortable because the
liability there's there's no other
people to share that liability when
there's a disagreement you're the one
who's getting subpoena as the broker
you're the one who's having to say I
wasn't practicing law I swear here's
where I advise them all to get their own
attorney but I did give them a legal
document and I did make edits to it
based on talking to them and I did give
them advice on how it would affect them
I do think that's a slippery slope to
practicing law without a
license but I have a question though so
like
and and you know this we've talked about
this before but there's this like race
to the bottom even amongst attorneys so
I'm like you know a a purchase agreement
that's been used by I think look there's
really bad Brokers out there you know
there's some Brokers out there that
might hand you something that you know
you should have reviewed but like if
you're dealing with like a relatively
large experienced broker that's used
that purchase agreement on hundreds of
transactions is that better or worse
than your like $2,000
flat fee discount purchase agreement
from a legit lawyer that you know got
their you know law degree at where did
uh Saul Goodman get his us Samoa
something like
that I don't know which one's better
that's a good question I'm I'm honestly
kind of thinking is it better to just
proceed on an Loi and have no purchase
agreement at all then have one where
there's no there's no quality control
because it could just include a whole
bunch of stuff in there that nobody
understands that hurts everyone or more
likely hurts one party but a bank won't
do that right like you have to have a
purchase agreement
for yeah and and the bank reviews for
their own protection so the bank um I've
seen approve some really terrible
agreements with edits but the edits only
protect the bank right so you know I
think understandably and I would fill
this way too I get it um I would think
well the bank's got lawyers and the
bank's lawyers are going to review it so
they wouldn't let me enter into
something insane but I mean I work with
those Bank lawyers and um I don't get
the the feeling that they're like
particularly well compensated or you
know they're not like going way out of
the box to try to protect they're
they're frankly in an adversarial
position to you as the the person taking
out the loan like they are protecting
the bank at your expense and so when
they're reviewing it they've come in
with this okay where are the assets how
can we make sure that when you stop
paying the bank we can come in and take
everything you have from you and the
seller so it's just a weird dynamic that
doesn't necessarily protect you at all
so I get the appeal I did have a broker
who was very kind and I had drafted a
purchase agreement for a deal that
didn't go through and so the seller had
gotten the agreement and a future buyer
came and and um same seller and the
broker called me and said can I use your
can I hire you to change your last
document to fit this buyer and I said no
no no I'm conflicted out because I've
already represented one potential buyer
I know some stuff I shouldn't you know I
can't I can't work for the seller you
know um that's a conflict sorry thank
you for asking and he said um well can I
buy the the transaction documents from
you can I just pay you a flat fee for
the purchase agreement and and I I won't
hire you to do it but like I will use it
myself and I was like I mean that's
something I'd never considered before
sure you know um because it had been
written for that particular Target you
know you know I think custom is always
the better way to go but like that's so
that's kind of the question right like
so some of these templated purchase
agreements you know I know some a member
of the business brokers of Florida the
BBF just put out their new asset
purchase agreement and they spent a lot
of money they spent a lot of money and
had a team of lawyers put it together
they had one attorney put the draft
together another one review it and
second review changes alterations like
they had a team of lawyers put it
together so like some of these are
pretty elaborate but like so it may be a
good document but again it's still not
tailored to your specific purpose so
it's it's tough I feel better about that
though than I do about just I mean
honestly broker that got something off
chat GPT yes and chat GPT isn't even
that bad because chat GPT is not going
to add the the risk of some random
non-lawyer agreement and really as a
lawyer your risk when you're drafting is
that you don't remove something that
shouldn't be in there like that's almost
the biggest risk and the second is you
don't add something that should be but
like having existing language that's in
there from some other use that just
stays as a legacy language and things is
so high risk that I almost like an open
AI purchase agreement more than I do um
using a really beautiful agreement that
a lawyer drafted for a totally different
matter because you know you've done that
right on open AI or like draft a
promisory note and it's like bullet
point one you know regular language it's
got you know 10 sentences at the end of
it but it's stuff that a regular person
can read and usually understand right
yeah for sure so okay so timeline wise
you know and so we're going to use so
like so many of the books out there you
know like m&a for dummies the harbor
Business Review books like all of that's
about these deals that are like 25 to
like there it is um I mean even that
book calls it out that it's like talking
about deals that are 25 to 100 million
do or $100 million up um so we're
talking about deals that are like sub 10
million sub five million really so like
a lot of people are like going for SBA
um so you're searching you find a deal
you like you get the NDA you sign the
NDA look at the Sim the uh initial
offering memorandum uh and then meet
with the seller I think in my opinion
from what I've seen that takes place in
like week one maybe two weeks tops what
do you think same yes I think it's very
important to not lose momentum so it
should take place quickly well and I
want to put I want to put a note on this
so not all businesses have a SIM and I
think there's a lot of there's a lot of
uh influencers out there a lot of great
people that are educating you know in
different ways and they they're really
pushing hard so look please if you're
listening to this if you are a buyer and
you want to be taken
seriously ask for the pieces that you
need to make decisions try not to just
use the terms that are being floated
around the internet because somebody
might not take you seriously like there
are Brokers out there that have been
doing this for 30 years and they don't
know what these influencers are pushing
so they hear you coming in using private
Equity terms and you're not a private
Equity person they're going to be like
okay this person has no idea what
they're talking about yeah so you might
not actually be asking for a Sim right
what you want is you want some
additional financial information you
want the last three years of the profit
and loss statement the balance sheet the
statement of cash flow you want tax
returns if you can get them that early
sometimes a broker will want you to meet
with a seller first um but these are the
things like and then like a an executive
summary like that's pretty much like the
bones of what's going to be in a Sim
um okay so NDA every deal every deal
you're going to sign NDA because they're
all confidential every deal you're going
to see something like a Sim either a
full Sim packet or the pieces and parts
an executive summary the financials
that's all week one then you have an
initial meeting with the seller uh we
talked about this on some of the
previous episodes like don't overdo it
like you're just getting to know the
seller at this point you want to make
sure that there's somebody that you know
they'll sell their baby to um okay but
then
Loi like how long does that take because
mine took six weeks like I you know I
guess it's is this like you know this
just kind of open right like so how long
you know let's put a timeline on a time
box to it like how much time do you
think it takes on average to do an Loi
that you get to like an agreement on and
it could be a range um sometimes people
just accept them uh as you can tell the
Lois that I put forth have everything in
them so that you could just be good and
go to closing um so there's not a lot of
future negotiation cost um so it's very
common for them to elicit conversation
which is half the point you know like
okay oh okay I I do also own the
building and you're now wanting to talk
about the rent you're going to pay when
you rent the office space from me and I
hadn't really thought about that yet so
um so there is some kind of eventual so
usually for for my clients goes Loi
conversation revised Loi sign so a week
two weeks um nice okay that's great yeah
I have had folks that really get into it
more and it's like every I mean that
deals fall apart there a lot and and you
know to your point in your experience I
think that that's good because they're
falling apart for real reasons you know
it's not like everybody just got tired
and mad at each other at the end um
which is the alternative it's that you
really didn't agree on one of the terms
and that's okay you don't have to you
know it's like yeah it's getting getting
to know the other person yeah okay so
that's great so so NDA Sim initial
review a week maybe two Loi probably two
weeks so you're like a month in at this
point so a month in you have an
agreement now I'm GNA make a bold a bold
claim here and I'm I'm very new to this
you are not so please correct me if you
disagree or maybe we just dis agree or
I'll abandon this Al together because I
have a very weak position on this but
but um you know if you're not going to
get an Loi if you're if you are
following the advice of a broker maybe
you have a buy side representative and
they're trying to get you to go to a
purchase agreement like it is more
legally binding than your Loi but I
would still in your mind think of it as
being more legally binding but kind of
squishy like an Loi like you're using it
but it's probably going to change a lot
and so maybe not a good reason to get
into a legally binding situation like
what are your thoughts where you yeah
I've definitely been hired I'm thinking
of um cases in particular where uh I've
been hired after a purchase agreement is
signed and I'm
like cool you know I'm done I can't do
anything you've already agreed to
everything so um that's uh not ideal uh
in those cases I I have offered an
amended purchase agreement um which will
essentially gut the concepts of the
purchase agreement identify that we're
still going to work on a definitive
agreement in the future where everyone
will put the real stuff in there and
expand um a contingency for your
diligence process that is ongoing like
perennial because usually when people
like what you're talking about right now
is um scrap the LOI just offer a real
simple broker style purchase agreement
and get the parties to agree and sign it
and be good um and in that there would
always be a diligence contingency but
you know you're you're the broker side
you want the deal to go through you
don't think they need that much time
during diligence you know everything
about the business and it's a good one
so you're gonna make that diligence
contingency like 30 days max you know
and um they're gonna not have an idea at
all about the significance of that and
they're going to blow through it because
you're corresponding they're still
asking for questions they're still
meeting um the conversations are active
and ongoing they're not even think about
the fact that all of a sudden one of
these Tuesdays they are in a binding
agreement to pay a million dollars for
this deal that they think they're still
just getting to know about um and that
sneaks up off people a ton so you know
if I'm the lawyer and I've got a buyer
and I'm dealing with that I'm going in
there to try to make sure that the
diligence contingency is as long as
possible if the other side won't agree
to some kind of like while documents are
still being exchanged it's going to be
perennially extended if they won't agree
to that then you know I'm calendaring it
and reminding them get it in writing
that we're extending this today um and
pushing it um as broad as possible so
that you can still and then you always
if there's financing involved you always
have to say um that you in any purchase
agreement if there's a delayed sign and
close even when I do it I I put my
documents together so they sign the
purchase agreement as soon as they come
to terms on it so it's off the table and
then the promisory note and all those
things get signed the day of closing so
I have big contingencies that say if I
can't get financing for any reason
whatsoever this I can void this so um in
the
pandemic uh there were a ton of sba7a
loans out and that had already like been
committed to uh and they put the kabash
on all of them so even things that were
about to close the next day um they
froze all the SBA financing and so all
of these people were under contractual
obligations to pay millions of dollars
for a a business that they had and they
had no way to fund it um because there
was no financing contingency so there
was a lot of litigation and stuff gotcha
okay so people people listening this to
will inevitably end up in a deal where a
broker is pushing hard on the broker
provided purchase agreement
and so some things that they should ask
for they should make sure that their due
diligence is at
least six weeks like so maybe I think
longer than that so we're talking a
pretty small deal right like if you're
you know if you've got a broker pushing
you to use a broker provided purchase
agreement on a $3 million deal like you
probably need to put your foot down and
like go get a lawyer um if it's a small
deal if it's under a million and you
really are committed to not spending the
money on a lawyer and you're going to
use a broker provided agreement so
sounds like they need to stretch out the
due diligence so to give themselves
plenty of time they need to make sure
that they add in a financing some kind
of a funding clause for the loan
anything else like how else can someone
protect themselves if they are going to
go this route and they're not going to
do an Loi and they're going to do a
purchase agreement right away before due
diligence if you are doing a purchase
agreement right away before diligence
you really really have to make it your
full-time job to monitor the deadline
associated with it and if you don't have
every single document you've asked for
at the end of the six week deadline or
whatever deadline you get for that
diligence contingency you need to in
writing say I want to avoid this
agreement like you have to go Draconian
on it because absent that it will go
super Draconian on you and you will be
committed and think about it from um a
bad broker's perspective if you have a
30-day diligence contingency and you're
just like Tick Tock waiting away and
somebody has offered you a list of
questions and you know maybe there's one
thing that they really shouldn't see
that might kill the deal you can just
sit on it for 31 days and they're
committed to buying the business um and
you haven't done anything fraudulent you
can give it to them in 31 day they were
the one who was dumb enough to sign a
purchase agreement and not void it when
they hadn't received every single
diligence request item that they they
asked for within that window so I just
think um because it's not presented as
clearly that it's such a big obligation
people don't understand how binding it
is is there any additional Clause where
if something materially affects the deal
in a bigger way they could still get out
of it I mean not really I'm thinking
back to like our our episode with Nathan
where he found out after closing that
the seller had signed up a bunch of of
annual contracts that he then had to
service without getting that Revenue
there was nothing he could have put into
the agreement that would have saved him
from that at that point well so what
he's supposed to have is a contract
where all of the representations and
warranties mirror the diligence process
so everything that they've told him in
diligence now is written into into the
contract as a legally binding promise
and then when it turns out they lied and
said there are no other obligations
other than what we have already told you
about
you know section 3.01 or whatever um
then he has a breach of contract claim
against them but since um I don't know
if he used a lawyer and he didn't it
didn't seem like he had a good agreement
so he would have had a tow hold for a
breach of contract claim and and so it's
twofold right like people exchange the
these diligence checklists and then I go
through and I read all of these
representations which are like legal
promises that are supposed to mirror the
diligence process and then when the
seller gets it if they actually read the
agreement which they usually do or their
um lawyer reads it with them it almost
always elist it's additional information
so you know you think you've had a good
diligence process but they go well there
is this thing you know before I just pin
the paper sign a legally binding promise
that this is everything maybe I should
point out that I do have these other you
know coupons that I gave or you know
these other big list of AR or this
person who did you know have a data
breach when she was our office admin six
years ago or you know and so it's
helpful because you're kind of putting
them in a corner to um make a promise
yeah so make sure if if a broker is
providing you with an agreement and you
are going to use it make sure you read
the section on the representations and
warrant the representations and
warrantees and I'm a big fan of some
kind of hold back earn out earn down
escrow like and what what that means at
a high level you know is that you're
going to put some portion some
percentage of the deal into an escro
account that's going to be held for a
period of time one year you know 18
months two years whatever um but that
way if something is just materially
different you have some type of a lever
to pull some kind of protection so so
yeah so it sounds like you know make
sure you have extra time for due
diligence if you're using a purchase
agreement in place of an Loi provided by
a broker with no attorney make sure you
have plenty of time for due diligence
make sure you um have a contingency for
getting your financing make sure you
really really really understand the Reps
and warrantees um make sure that you
have something some kind of a protection
post close an ounce of prevention is
worth a pound of cure there so like you
don't want to have to enforce your
purchase agreement anyways so I would
say if you're doing that whatever um if
you're go if you're moving forward to
buy like a Million Dollar business and
you don't want to spend $7,000 on a
lawyer you are quite tolerant of risk so
um you probably got to watch yourself
and make sure you can buckle down and
really dig into the diligences um even
more aggressively than the average
person would so okay so we're four weeks
in you have an Loi or at least some type
of an agreement signed that lays out a
price you're starting due diligence due
diligence is going to take probably six
weeks right and I think most cases six
weeks that's also the exact same amount
of time that most preferred lenders take
to put to put the the the loan together
so as soon as you get that signed
agreement you're going to apply for the
loan and start due diligence at the same
time right and then so after that six
weeks everything looks good your
contingency ends on the on the diligence
period you're moving towards
closing what do you think two weeks to
get to closing at least two weeks it's
usually Bank stuff that um pushes it I I
would say the best thing you can do you
know I've had really responsive buyers
who respond within like 20 minutes to
any request from the bank or from me or
from the other side and those sail
through almost as fast as they want them
to you know um if you have a preferred
lender and you've got a good bank um but
uh absent that if you're in the middle
of tax season like we have been they
have been really dragging out
um because you know it just takes it
takes longer to get responses but yeah I
think two weeks is reasonable they say
45 days if you're a cash buyer you can
close faster if you have to do some
extensions it can take longer but it
sounds like a good time frame to plan on
is three months 90 days yeah to get from
you know NDA to closing I agree yep so a
number that I threw out yesterday
because I I I'm talking to a client who
is going to be doing multiple
Acquisitions and we're trying to budget
out for the future so I threw out a
number of about $30,000 per deal these
are going to be a little bit larger
deals so that 30,000 is to cover
diligence um you know Financial legal
diligence and uh contracts it's just
like a ballpark per deal so we know what
we're what we're burning if we walk away
from deals um on these smaller deals you
mentioned $7,000 for purchase agreement
what do you think someone should have in
their pocket in their bank account uh
for diligence and contracts on a deal
that is small smaller say under under a
million under two million something like
that well I live right in that realm so
under two million is like really
different for me than under a million um
because under a million's really small
um you know but also I paid a lot less
than that for my house and like I
definitely paid to get an inspection and
signed a legal contract and did a title
search and things like that so if you'll
pay $10,000 in closing costs on a house
like you should be willing to pay
$110,000 on a you know closing on a
business that's you know at least based
on averages in the US two to three times
more than the house you live in and the
house you live in you can like you can
walk through it knock on walls and stuff
the business you may have never even
seen in person so there's warranted some
additional inquiry um but uh so I would
say um I think the um this book even
said like 25k for legal which I was like
I don't know if that's true and for
small deals uh like under um a million I
try to really say you can run it
yourself as much as you want as the
buyer and you should you should not
delegate you cannot delegate you have to
do it yourself if you want to keep it
cheap and then you know 10K legal
probably tops and then um uh it depends
on if you get a qov it's hard to find a
affordable quality of earnings report
from the CPA um and it just depends on
the client's uh tolerance and how good
there I I can't tell you how many
people's just like tax preparers are
also Moonlighting as free qov
providers they'll say I sent the books
over to my accountant and they said it
looks good and you're like what is that
person doing that for you for free and
they don't know what they're looking at
like why would they know that um so uh
you know if you do that if you use your
existing Tax Repair and you feel like
that's good enough and you can just use
a point and shoot lawyer and then do
everything else yourself then you you
should be um getting in under 15K but I
mean you should at least be spending
$15,000 to try to secure um your assets
so actually it's funny that you
mentioned that because in order to join
the business Buyers Club you do have to
have $115,000 or access to $155,000
minimum to cover due diligence like I'm
we're fine if you have a game like if
you got really great experience and you
think you're going to be a great
business owner and you want to bring an
investor in to cover your down payment
that's fine but you have to have $15,000
to cover diligence because if you're
going to try to skip diligence like
that's just not something we want to get
into yeah it's so dangerous it's just
buying this black box and and I mean
it's shortsighted because you're going
to pay for that
$115,000 in the first couple weeks of
poorly running the business you don't
know anything about because you didn't
do diligence right no and again go back
to the episode with Nathan platter who
you know he he did what he thought was
really good diligence um you know and
then now is burning he told us on on
cameras go back watch the episode I
think it was like 5,000 a month
something like that like you'll you know
what did you say you said such a great
thing and I've heard it before but I
don't use it enough an ounce of
prevention is pound of cure yeah worth a
pound of cure so it's I mean like it's
very shortsighted um to and I mean that
in both ways I'm not just trying to like
Jin up money for service providers I
really think that you know a lot of
people don't hire me because I'm not
offering to take diligence off their
plate because I'm like I'm not going to
be running this business you need to
figure it out I'm here to answer
questions I'm here to offer tips and
guidelines and checklists and structure
but I cannot be you can't just Farm it
out give me a data room access and go I
did diligence I'm G to check that book
uh off like you have to do it you wanna
why why do you want to buy a business to
run if you're not wanting to run the
business well and so here's something
that I think is really interesting
because there's a a broker in my office
and he is fantastic I've learned so much
from him and he's got so much experience
but he comes from a time where and he
and I had this funny conversation so if
he hears it it'll be okay um but he
comes from a time where business people
businessmen business women were buying
businesses so his whole opinion is like
H if it's under a million they're going
to do their due diligence they're going
to go down the general ledger line by
line they're going to go through the
bank statement line by line and ask a
question about every single line item
and I had to tell him that's not really
the case anymore like with the SBA
program with all these training groups
coming out there are a lot of creatives
that are buying businesses and they
don't want to look at bank statements
they don't want to understand the p&l
and um so your broker may tell you you
don't need due diligence but this
because in their mind they're used to
Decades of buyers who are Savvy
Financial analytical and they're not
used to dealing with creatives or you
know even this like millennial
generation
that um you know just doesn't have that
attention to detail into into how a
business is run by the numbers you know
we you know lot so many people are you
know more emotional and relationship
oriented which you can run a business
you can be an exceptional entrepreneur
with a focus on on emotion and that EQ
but to buy the business you need to
understand the numbers and if you don't
know if you don't do it you got to
Outsource it yeah and if somebody
is uh trying to sell you on taking that
off your plate like that's don't spend
that money take that and put that money
back in your pocket cuz you're the one
who has to know the contracts and the
vendors and who the phone services
through and what you know what software
they use and when that software
subscription renews
and that's a you just made a really
great distinction because I didn't I
didn't speak clearly with what I was
just saying when I say Outsource it you
can't Outsource it and not know it what
I mean when I say Outsource it you need
to Outsource the The Mucky muck of the
work to somebody who can explain it to
you thoroughly yes like somebody who's
gonna teach
you can't you can't just push it off and
never look at it like you either need to
learn it on your own and understand it
on your own or Outsource it to someone
who can then teach you and explain to
you I had a client last year um U who's
entrepreneur buying business with um not
experienc like you're talking about and
he said said multiple times um I'm just
really bad at admin so I'm not going to
do that I'm I'm really bad at admin and
I was like that is the thing you need to
be good at that is maybe the only thing
that you need to be good at if you're
buying a business with a bank loan just
the process of buying the business and
then gosh running the business so it's
kind of all
admin absolutely and and this is where I
I know that I'm a contrarian in this I
do believe that everybody could be a
business owner you know and maybe that's
like maybe that's just naive and you
know hopelessly optimistic but you know
I think you can figure it out I've seen
a lot of really successful people come
from various backgrounds with various
personality types uh it's definitely
easier if you understand the admin but
like if you don't you have to know the
pieces you have to know who needs to be
on your team and maybe you know maybe
you're not you know maybe you're not the
main character you know maybe you uh
maybe You Don't Own 100% of the business
you acquire because you need that admin
you need that analyst you need the
marketer salesperson and you maybe you
have to chop it up to to be successful
yeah yeah but recognizing your own
deficiencies and getting enough into the
weeds that you can properly delegate to
people who have the expertise is is I
mean it's no small feat I haven't had to
do it um and it's hard it looks terrible
so um but people do it and you have to
so I think that this was a really
thorough summary that we have done here
on the timeline what to expect when to
expect it and how much to expect to pay
for it yeah so there we are acquisition
101 right this has been episode 11 Sarah
and I are back from a couple weeks off
and post tax season post massive Eclipse
party and talking about the steps
timeline and price of doing a deal and
why most businesses really do fail even
before due diligence thanks for
listening if you got some value from
this uh like subscribe leave a comment
on what you would like to learn about
the acquisition process or who you'd
like for us to talk to and uh see you
next
time I got to make it just for my kids
for kids kid that's and promise my
brother soon as he fin this we do it
bigger than anybody ever